[Music]
so please welcome daniel
schmachtenberger
thank you
so daniel if we just
fast forward to
2020 2030 2040 2050
just really go into the future
what would an ideal hospital look like
well i think in this open space a lot of
ideas were being brought up about that
yesterday as well
i think everybody has a clear sense that
the
environmental design and environmental
psychology of the space is a huge part
of it
the airflow the lighting both natural
lighting and
the right spectrum and the right amount
of lumens and
really paying attention to the way the
environment is affecting the health and
the experience of the people
in the space so the actual design of the
infrastructure of the building itself i
think
the nature of the amount of
time and also the amount of time that
the providers get to spend with people
and also their training for the quality
of time and how they spend it
i think there's a lot of things we know
about the tech that we want to see in
terms of
both much higher quality and less
invasive diagnostics
and there's a lot of diagnostic tech
that
by some of those dates will be online
that is now that will make a huge
difference
the kind of dream of theranos that they
didn't write didn't really have the tech
for there
there is tech that will achieve things
like that there's a company called gene
radar
uh coming out of a company called
nanobiosim that
i think will probably make huge progress
in that time and other tech like it
where
instead of needing reagents to be able
to do blood labs we can simply do
chip based amplification and so a single
drop of blood can be able to measure
every biometric and if you imagine
not having the cost associated then just
run every biometric every time on
everyone
run big data analysis on an individual
person longitudinally over their life
plus on lots of people and that's not
just in the hospital that can be
decentralized so that
we start finding early disease
indicators and being able to prevent
most things so i think there's a bunch
of examples of better diagnostics and
machine learning
that can augment the human doctor and
healthcare provider capacity so that the
healthcare provider can be
much more focused on actually connecting
to people and taking in the kind of
diagnostic info that humans are uniquely
good at that machines don't do as good a
job at
which is less biometric specified and
more being able to get the gestalt of
the person that lets you even know what
to look for and how to interpret it
so there's a lot of things like this
that we could talk about
one of them was mentioned yesterday that
i
just feel like bringing up is
the idea that the hospital would feel
more like a sacred place like a temple
of some sort seems to be at the heart if
if we put that at the heart of the
consideration a lot of other things make
more sense
yeah and when you talk about heart-based
medicine
obviously we want a medicine that is uh
really excellent in terms of operations
and
we want a medicine that's really
excellent in terms of the actual science
and the technology of it but what's
motivating all of it is the sacredness
of human life and human experience
and wanting to be able to support people
who have the highest quality experience
in the highest quality capacity to
offer what others to offer while they're
here
and so that everyone in the healthcare
space remembers
and continuously that that's actually
why they're there
and the entire design is around
supporting that experience
you know you were talking about
experiences where people died in your
care
and where they died in ways that were
really beautiful
versus painful based on the nature of
the care
so if you think about a hospital as a
place where people will be born
and people will die and people will be
brought back from death
and people will have the chance to have
a totally different life trajectory
based on the care they get
like the sacredness of life is more on
the altar there than maybe anywhere else
and um i i would like to see something
where
the doctors and nurses go through a
ritual before they actually enter
every time not it becomes a dogma
because the moment
the moment that there is an
intrinsically recognized dharma that
becomes a protocol and becomes a dogma
then
obviously just becomes performative life
listen and you either do the
performative thing or just reject it
but if someone actually kind of
reconnected to the most beautiful
experiences they had in medicine the
most heart-wrenching
experiences why they were there what the
hippocratic oath was
and why they're there the way that would
affect
the quality of the interactions and not
just
from the point of view that the
patient's experience would be better but
also the actual quality of the care
would make a tremendous difference so
we could talk about a lot of things
based on specifically what we have the
state might be available in those
different timelines
what things we could do retrofitting
existing hospitals versus where we need
to build them from the ground up
what things where we're still thinking
of a hospital versus where we start to
think about decentralizing health care
into all of
life so that's a start
wonderful thank you so many open
questions let's um
you were putting the temple in the
center
so maybe let's start at the center
and i believe it's what you're
describing is um
that the subjective experience
of a true dedication of a true interest
of the healthcare provider so rather
than busy being busy with themselves but
actually truly caring about the person
they're
under in their care
that subjective experience will improve
the quality of care
not only in terms of making less
mistakes like this is
i realize it's the first time when i you
know
i learned to make all these
prescriptions and so here you go and
here's another one and here's another
one here's another one and you're just
describing
and then i realized suddenly my kids
were in hospital
and i sat there and said like okay all
right now my kid's at hospital next one
next
and then i went um do i really want that
such an important moment to realize that
when i
see children and i make prescription
based on what their disease
is or i make a prescription for somebody
that i have a personal direct relation
with it's somehow there's a moment of
there so the quality i completely agree
that the quality of care
when we talk about patient safety a big
topic today
we talk about patient safety we improve
the way
that healthcare providers show up this
will
improve the quality of care will improve
the safety of the patient
but it will also improve patient
satisfaction
and so there's a subjective experience
on the other side
so what could you see as
steps taken well now let's start with
the end in mind
what would you see in you know 20 30 40
50 what might be the way that
what might describe or constitute the
relation between a healthcare provider
and a patient
so you mentioned less mistakes
i think getting rid of
all of the avoidable ietrogenic illness
is
it would take a few things increased
presence on the part of the doctors
and pharmacists and nurses is going to
make a huge difference to them
it's not only that though it's also the
medical training up front it's also
removing the financialization
of medicine that ends up influencing the
training and the incentive structures of
the doctors as long as the hospital has
to have the doctors seeing more people
per day or in private practice you have
to see more people per day the mistakes
are just going to go up so
some of it can be addressed at the
bottom up level of things individual
doctors can do
some of it really has to be addressed at
the top down level of the
of the major top-down institutions that
are affecting medicine and optimizing
for something other than quality of care
and if we have trillions of dollars a
year optimizing for things other than
quality of care
compared to the relatively small level
of a few doctors
that it's actually an asymmetric warfare
against
health right as long as at a federal
level we want to optimize gdp
and we met we think about gdp as a sign
of the success of the country
sick people are better for gdp than
healthy people are in a narrow
point of view in terms of medicine and
obviously this is the same for a
pharmaceutical company's incentive or
things like that if if we could just
prevent medicine
by making healthy people we would
obviously
have the best system of health care and
it would totally tank gdp from both a
pharmaceutical and hospital revenue
point of view as well as from the
revenue of
food drug et cetera companies that make
more money off addiction
so there's systemic factors as well as
kind of individual practitioner factors
that have to be addressed to
remove hydrogenic disease
and then as you're mentioning the
the increased presence of a practitioner
with
a person who is in one of the most
disturbing positions people can be in
where
the quality of their life or their loved
one's life is like
up in the air and they don't have the
technical expertise to know how it's
going to go
and so they're trusting a stranger with
the most precious thing to them
actually feeling the care and the
presence and the attention
of that stranger is going to make a huge
difference where
even if the thing is incurable
the actual experience of someone is a
terminal value in and of itself
independent of how that translates to
objective outcomes
and it will translate to objective
outcomes both in terms of
increased diagnostic insight on the part
of the practitioner and
a psychologically
better state and less stress on the part
of the
patient is going to help their healing
process
so i mean this is just kind of recapping
why
heart-based medicine matters right
and then um
i don't think any of that answered your
question your question was
how do we what would constitute the
relation between the healthcare provider
and the patient
and so you mentioned quality of care and
we started at
kind of avoiding mistakes but we may
just as we
look at disease on a systemic level we
look at mistakes
in terms of heart-based medicine we want
to look at kind of
shift the attention a little bit away
from disease
towards health so on on that systemic
level we may want to
ask what is quality of care yeah
when we when we shift it towards the
positive outcome towards the potential
and how might that be a constituent of
the relationship between
so let me do a long-range version of
this i'm not going to try and specify
the timeline we'll just do
a it will generally be hopefully
trending in this direction if it's on
the right path
so let's say we look at the trend of
technological automation to automate
things that we can proceduralize
that'll affect some things in medicine
and hopefully it will because that would
be great there are some things that
machines can do as well or better
and it won't affect other things and if
it does it'd be a bummer because they do
it less well
but outside of medicine most of the jobs
that people like the least are
some of the ones that are most available
to technological automation
because it the more procedural something
is the easier it is to automate
the more procedural it is also the less
creativity and learning is involved
which means we have the less
less intrinsic motive for a human to
feel like they can self-actualize there
and so as we progress
to more technological automation and
more categories we also start to change
a lot of the underlying assumptions
within market theory that we need people
to do the jobs
so we need to make it to where the
people need the jobs
well we don't need people to do a lot of
the jobs then we can also
start to create more of commonwealth
resources that
take care of people's needs to have a
system that is more focused on the
intrinsic incentive of people than the
extrinsic incentive
when you want to get people to when you
have to get people to do shitty labor
stuff you have to extrinsically incent
them when more of that's automated
then we get to facilitate what is
actually intrinsically interesting and
meaningful for people and it's not just
playing video games all the time
if they get to be facilitated to
recognize that their short time here can
actually mean something
and i think the things that people will
most want to do have to do with
connection creativity and healing and so
i think there will be a lot more people
in the healing
professions and i think
as we think less and less in terms of
how do i think of this as a way to
financially support myself and more in
terms of if finances were already
supported what would i want to do
a lot of people want to do things that
involve connecting with other people in
ways that
contribute to the quality of their life
and that's everything from like
music therapy and art therapy and
psychospiritual practice
to uh training people's physical bodies
and
like that so i think the role of the
doctor will become largely decentralized
to a lot of other things that are
promoting well-being more than just
dealing with the after effects of not
promoting well-being
and similarly to where when we say
removing iatrogenic disease requires not
just
change on the doctor part but also the
structural
incentives that lead to genetic disease
if we want to obsolete as much of
medicine as possible we have to look at
what the upstream causes of the problems
are so
obviously if we if we don't just look at
health care but we look at the embedding
environment of things that affect
people's health and we're pumping
billions of tons of glyphosate and other
pesticides and herbicides and petrol
chemical toxins into the atmosphere
and into people's food supply and water
supply continuously and
embedding them in the manufacturing
process in the carpet in the paint and
where all of our
environments are actually toxic to the
way we genetically evolved we
genetically evolved to an environment
that didn't have organophosphates
and you know neonicotinoids
being able to change those things also
obsoletes so much
of the things that are upstream
contributing
to so much of the chronic complex
illness
then you start to think about the
changes in agriculture to actually
re-mineralize topsoils and affect the
microbiome of the topsoils and the
quality of the you know food that's
coming out and
again we have to ask can we have healthy
people and
in a society where almost everyone is
stressed out
due to macroeconomic pressures and due
to sociopolitical instability
continuously
and so
there's there's still going to be
situations where no matter how well we
design
it somebody falls and hits their head
and we have to deal with that or
something that we haven't been able to
tend to comes up but
most of the causes of illness are
actually structurally induced at scale
in ways that are affecting everyone and
you actually can't even avoid currently
so i'm answering the question about the
relationship between the practitioner
partly saying most of the things
practitioners are currently looking at i
would like to not exist at all because
we're dealing with them upstream
both by doing health promotion and by
stopping the things that are doing
health degradation
so that's the first part then we can get
into what
the uh when disease is manifesting and
we need to deal with it what that looks
like but we would like to mostly just
shrink that category
um thank you so before we go we will
definitely need to talk about the
the wider picture of health care or
healthy life um and the question of how
might we in if we were to be able to
redesign the health care system
and just completely kind of clean the
table start out of the box what would it
what could it look like
and those will be questions that we
would need to answer and and let's come
back to those so
if you allow let's stay a little bit
longer with with the
environment that is kind of closer to us
right now before we redesign everything
yeah so um when i look at the
the relation between the healthcare
provider and and the patient
one of the obvious changes right now
and you alluded to this is the
automation of of healthcare
so more and more processes that you know
just take
knowledge there's all the things that i
learned
in medical school in terms of data to be
you know memorized
um all the effort it took in in the
initial years of
my existence to go through paper cards
and finding that paper in paris and
filling out a form and ordering it from
this library in paris and four weeks
later the paper would arrive and now
everything is available
online and we have search engines and
text mining and we can integrate all of
this and
some fantastic new technologies already
collecting
information and processing this
information for me
so there's that's one element so so how
am i going to deal with data now i
sometimes feel like i'm in a data crisis
actually i
yeah in the beginning it was a problem
to find information now i feel like
i have enough i can't process more so
that's that's a huge development and
another huge development is that
the technological impact so all the
devices that we have all the techniques
and technologies that we have
that actually seem like seem to have
more authority
than my own clinical assessment
so i used to you know actually do a
crazy thing and examine
patients you know now when i examine a
patient um and if there's something i
would have to validate my finding by
some kind of technology
so if i feel that there's some you know
something or you know i feel the liver
is a little bit larger than i would
expect and
the next step would be to to get an
ultrasound to validate that that's the
case
and it used to be that that that was the
finding
so somehow this the technology has
become is
is becoming the reference point it's the
kind of the objective measure and
whatever we do as human beings is
measured against
technology
this is worrying to me
do you see that you know the the
profession of the physician will be
replaced
by technology at some point are we going
to have a robot where i just you know
like the little photo cameras that you
had at stations where you sit in you get
four pictures and
so i just walk into some station or some
office and then
i put my finger in there take a bit of
blood and maybe take a little swab of my
my epithelium in the mouth and and they
go and two minutes later i get some
report
is this the future of medicine
hopefully yes and no there are things
that
machine learning can do really better
than human cognition there are things
that human cognition do that machine
learning can't do
at all whether we get to artificial
general intelligence
or not obviously changes that story a
bit because then we're
talking about things that are less like
machines and more like
other kinds of beings
i don't think we're close to that so
we're just talking about machine
learning and machine learning mostly
that is narrow in type
and so what i think that means
is that
the machine learning and the diagnostics
augment our capacity radically in good
ways in the way already your stethoscope
and your microscope and your you know
whatever tools your glasses you're
wearing right now are augmenting
your capacity and it's just continued
tools that can do that
so we learn new metrics new biometrics
all the time parts of the body we didn't
even know existed or parts of physiology
or new types of proteins and then
they're like the center of everything
and they're super important
we can anticipate that that continues
for a long time
that 10 years from now nobel prizes will
be won about like breakthrough stuff
that we don't even know about right now
that will be the main stuff to look at
and so there's no way we're testing that
right now and there's no way that
machine learning is paying attention to
that
and yet some of it still comes through a
kind of heuristic or intuitive
sensibility
where you're feeling the liver and you
have some sense
even if the liver enzymes don't indicate
it or whatever some other test that
we don't currently have does so
i think that the human capacity for
general intelligence
which includes intuition and things
beyond what we currently have
metrics on becomes increasingly
important
as we're able to offload more of the
specialized narrow intelligence
so then the role of the doctor the
practitioner is largely
one that intermediates between really
being able to connect with the patient
in a holistic
generalized intuitive and
obviously enough cognitive knowledge to
even know how to use this database way
but then doesn't depend exclusively on
their own
memory we already don't we already
offload it to books it's just
much better versions of books and papers
and
you know when we think about the idea of
the information singularity
there can be so much information that no
one can be a specialist in any topic
there's a hundred thousand journal
articles a year in the topic of my
specialty so
already humans are irrelevant in the
information ecology
we don't really need to like the data
isn't what informs our choices
there the meaning of being able to put
the data of lots of things together does
and the
and the meaningfulness is a second or
third derivative of the data if we can
have the machines not just
data mine and find the articles but also
be able to make sense of what a lot of
those articles together inform as far as
treatment goes
so one of the things i want to see the
technology get a lot better at doing is
being able to do the kind of processing
it can so that what you're studying
is a higher order synthesis of the
information out there that you actually
can keep up with
so i see an information singularity much
faster than i see
a meaningfulness which is a derivative
of the information singularity which
then the doctors are going to be
paying attention to and the researchers
are working on helping to make sense of
factoring general intelligence so
the fact that we will be able to use
increasingly good cameras on an iphone
to look at a skin condition use image
recognition to automatically diagnose
the thing at a distance like that's
awesome
and there there are both things that
that won't do
in terms of physiologic diagnosis
and in terms of the quality of
connection
and so and both of those are very
important so um
i think we were talking the other day a
little bit about how
important it is that we don't automate
in ways that lead to more isolation
especially in the name of healthcare
when isolation is one of the number one
causes of health care issues in the
first place
thank you so when you when you talk
about the availability of technology and
how this technology may
kind of support our decision making and
will make it easier for us to
provide meaningful health care
and we talked about the temple as in the
center of the
hospital if you like
is there a sacred space for the human
being as a healer a space that can
structurally not be
taken on by automation
um yes
i think it's i think it's obvious um
again we have to question like let's
separate the topic of
artificial general intelligence or
silica-based life because now we're
talking about life
and whether that is possible ever or not
in terms of the
theoretical possibility of it and what
the
negative implications of silica-based
life trying to share a biosphere with a
hydrocarbon-based life might be like
that that's so not near if ever we can
take that off and so really then we're
talking about
human connection of being able to
connect with someone who can actually
care about you
and machines that are simply doing input
output processing
we obviously want to extend our capacity
with machines and the
healthcare the center of it is actually
care
so this care so we have the temple
where the sacred space we have care as
the primary
ingredient of the relation between the
healthcare provider
and the patient something that remains a
human
environment something that remains a
capacity in quality
so if this is this is something that can
be established already
in can be promoted already in the
existing healthcare system
now you were alluding already to
well yeah but care is not
limited or confined to either the
consultation room or
the hospital as really
whenever a doctor is needed we're too
late when we talk about health
so we've already reached a threshold
where
several non-linear processes have have
scaled up and the threshold has been
reached and now
the dis-ease has become symptomatic
so we're way too far downstream
so what we really wish to see is if we
want to promote health is to address
these health issues more upstream
you already alluded to agriculture
finances
social interactions so what are these
areas
so if we're if we're kind of moving from
what is an ideal hospital
to what is an ideal healthcare system
how would that change our perspective
what are these elements as we think
about moving forward we need to
think about our actual evolutionary
environment in terms of what our
genes were selected to actually do well
in
um because our future environment will
be different than that but it has to not
be misaligned with that right we've
created a world in which we're actually
genetically misfit
in really important ways so so we have
to consider this
when we think about the evolutionary
environment of humans the first thing is
we're social primates
and we for all of our evolutionary
history we're in bands and tribes with
extremely close
high trust interaction with lots of
other humans
and i mean we can look at the
how that affects via physical touch and
microbiome sharing and pheromone sharing
to the actual uh attachment theory of it
but
and it's gonna go beyond any of those
specific mechanisms
that's foundational to physical and
psychological health
and so we're not just talking about how
the infrastructure
will work we're also talking about how
the social structures work
i think it's really insightful to
contemplate
how many people you trust as much as
anyone in a tribe would have trusted
everyone they knew
because most people don't have anyone
that they feel like they know
as well or knows them as well or they
can trust as much as humans evolved
being able to trust all the people they
knew
and i don't want to over romanticize
it's not that there weren't difficulties
that were associated but
the kind of fierce egalitarianism tribes
had to have to be able to function
together well like in a tribe you can't
have
right left antipathy and stay together
right you can't have internal defection
you actually can't even get away with
lying because everyone's going to tell
there's a forced transparency
at that small scale and so
we actually need extraordinarily high
trust environments for psychological
health and we need psychological health
for physiological health
so that's one example so when we just
stay with the social interaction for now
and that's one of your
favorite topics is how to what is the
impact of a societal development
on them on various factors so if if in
this conversation we focus on health
what would be key societal developments
that we would like to see
again kind of time warping forwards
through 2050 what would we like to see
in place
in in our societies that
would reduce the
healthcare the attention in healthcare
facilities as we have them today
so could we kind of address some of the
problems that we see in hospitals now
already upstream
it's funny to kind of think about what
examples to use because it's pretty much
everything
it's like every building material we use
almost every building material out gases
volatile organic compounds from petrol
derivatives that are either neurotoxins
endocrine disruptors or carcinogens
so it's the restructuring of the entire
materials economy and material supply
chain to not be polluting the indoor and
outdoor environment
it's that the the actual
photic spectrum of the light that we're
in is unhealthy for us because we don't
just
photosynthesize vitamin d nitric oxide
and
uh cortisol and so many other things are
regulated by not just the total amount
of light but specific frequencies of
light and timing of light it's
like the
the nuclear family home structure the
nature of
economies of scale moving agriculture
far away where even if it was organic
which it generally isn't
it's old it's been actually undergoing
entropy since being picked for a pretty
long time
which means nutrient decay
let alone lack of interaction with the
soil that not only has a kind of
psychological regeneration but
microbiotic effects like
we can see that market forces
move the world to a place that optimizes
for market forces
and they optimize for addiction and
comfort rather than health or well-being
and i think this is a really important
thing is that
comfort and happiness or are not the
same thing
but as soon as we one of
one of the effects of kind of the
enlightenment
was moving into the domain of
objectivism and things we could measure
but we can actually measure metrics of
comfort like how bouncy the shocks in a
car
are or whatever more than we can measure
subjectivity which we can't measure at
all
and it gets into existentialism of what
is a meaningful human experience
and so we start optimizing for comfort
and you actually make shitty people when
you optimize for comfort because
psychologically good people are people
that can actually hold a certain
resilience in the presence of discomfort
so you look at the wisdom traditions
that had sweat lodges and ayahuasca
ceremonies and combo ceremonies and
sundances and vision quests which were
all
actually induced really intense
discomfort to be able to
find a self-transcendence in the
presence of it
in the same way that you don't get
strong people by not lifting weights
right you actually have to hormetically
stress the system to upregulate its
regulatory capacity
you have to psychologically stress the
emotional system to learn emotional
intelligence and
so there's so much of the in the name of
comfort that is just actually making
maximally entropic humans
and the same with like supposedly market
theory says people will demand real
things
that are actually going to enrich the
quality of their life like food and
whatever
and then that will create a basis for
people to create supply
and the best supply will end up getting
up regulated but of course
as soon as we start recognizing
economies of scale on the supply side
and the supply side becomes a much
bigger
organism than the demand side and it is
going to benefit from more profit
now it wants to figure out how to
manufacture artificial demand that
wasn't there
so then the business has the goal of
maximize lifetime revenue of a customer
and i maximize lifetime revenue of a
customer by driving addiction starting
in childhood
so if i can have social media and
entertainment that's maximally addictive
it figures out psychologically exactly
how to have the
right type of dings to get you back on
and make you feel miserable if you don't
have it and do the same thing with food
and etc
then we can have the plausible
deniability i'm providing what people
want yes
after you drove addiction in them using
asymmetric information and narrative and
technology warfare to drive that
addiction
but this does not create healthy or
happy people are good society
so you actually have to change the whole
nature of perverse incentive and market
dynamics writ large
to be producing goods and services
that are actually supporting the health
and well-being and integrity of people
in society
the redesign is pretty much everything
[Music]
so if i
if i just you know put this into a
pediatrician's kind of way
making it simple then
what i understand from you is that the
entire concept
of healthcare as a service
that is being paid for including all the
products that are being
that are part of this service come along
with this service
is not in line with the
with with the concept of health as
you're describing it
so all of this works as long as we have
disease
so if we have a problem to be solved if
we have a disease and we give it a name
and we give it a label
that allows us then to say if you have
that disease then you need this kind of
diagnostics and therefore you need these
sort of machines and therefore you need
these sort of treatments
congratulations here sincerely thank you
very much
so that is that is one um
this is one aspect
and the other is when we actually want
health
rather than the absence of disease then
all of this
is is a misfit so whatever we have
constructed in terms of
healthcare system trying to overcome
disease
as a system is not useful if
if we're actually turning our focus
towards health is that
i mean it's funny even if we just think
about disease diagnosis
i think most of the actual diseases that
we have diagnostics for
are made up they're fit their fictions
so obviously adhd is a fiction that is
just making childhood a disease
and it is
take take kids
have parents pay no attention to them
pay like if you think about what the
school is the way that we have it
structured
it's these p these little people don't
make money yet
and so they are
possibly future assets in the financial
system but right now they're liabilities
or
or debts on the future system so we want
the least number of productive class
people to monitor the most of impossible
so one teacher to 30 of them
typically a low paid person because
someone that could do something more
profitable we'd rather than generating
more profit
to get them to the point where they're
part of the productive class and as soon
as they're too old to be the productive
class then again we want to ship them
off somewhere where
one low-paid person takes care of lots
of them
like so we start with that
and the school system that doesn't
facilitate their interest in anything
forces them to be interested in totally
uninteresting breaks their interest
in life as a result so then they want to
play video games and
watch porn or whatever and then we say
that's the way that's what human nature
is there's only human nature after we
broke it
right so then we medicate that as a
disease because that's also a super
profitable thing to do and then that
creates the beginning of a nitrogenic
cascade where the
ritalin the side effects of the ritalin
are going to need an ssri later and then
are going to need a benzo
and then that person's for life
but the profitability is quite high in
terms of lifetime revenue
because if i drive rather than helping
people be healthy
if i override their system in a way
that's going to cause ongoing addiction
because they can't get off that benzo
because they're going to have rolling
panic attacks if they do way worse than
their anxiety initially ever was
but the side effects of that are another
drug that we also sell that's just
called an upsell or a cross cell which
is just good business
so like obviously adhd is a
disease
most psychiatric diagnoses it would be
way more useful to think about it
differently
but also like every complex chronic
disease
they're diseases in terms of
rheumatoid arthritis we call it a
disease or ms or alzheimer's
they don't have the same cause if i see
10 different people with ms there and i
actually found
out what's going on because right now we
don't know what's going on at all so the
disease just allows us to know
what symptomatic drugs or military drugs
we're going to do but we can't cure any
of them
but if i want to say what's actually
going on the patho etiology is different
in every case
because they're multifactorial and
they're not the same set of factors
and so the fact that there's a cluster
of biomarkers and a cluster of symptoms
that i can make a
a disease title for to then know what
drug to prescribe and insurance can do
that thing doesn't mean that that tells
me anything about the pathophysiology of
it
so even in so far as i'm thinking about
the disease i see ms i don't i don't
know when i hear ms all i know is
okay
so there's some kind of autoimmune
neurodegenerative stuff going on
this system was exposed to some things
that created dysregulation
deviations from homeodynamics it
probably led to more susceptibility to
more dysregulation
that eventually reached a threshold that
had symptomology where there was
probably pathophysiology going on for
years or decades ahead of time
and for this person with ms it was a
mold exposure
30 years ago that left mycotoxins that
changed
cytokine profiles and whatever that then
10 years later they had a micro tbi from
a car accident and then a divorce dress
that threw them over and now it's ms
and in somebody else it was a tick-borne
lime exposure and then some food
poisoning
in guatemala and some glyphosate and
then some other emotional stressor
so to actually be able to cure it i need
to know that stuff which the title ms
doesn't give me
so not only do we want to move to health
promotion like we want to even think
about disease in a reasonable way
that is so interesting
this is so interesting because the way
we do studies at least when when i look
at the studies that
this is the classic type of clinical
studies what we what we see is that
that there is uh there are basically two
observations so there's
uh there's a starting point and an end
point and then we assume that there's a
linear association between the two
and it seems that as we are as we are
learning more um
as there is in uh there's more insight
into how we might be able to calculate
non-linear associations and we're
recognizing that
that probably a lot of what is happening
during this time of observation in a
classic clinical trial
what we observe there is is very much
dependent on what happened before this
trial and all the things that you're
actually describing
and the heterogeneity that that is is
real
um is not usually captured in the kind
of typical table one
in a paper saying you know what is the
distribution of sex and gender and
ethnicity so this is way way more
complex than that
and we haven't even started to come to
grips with the complexity of what
what the regulatory mechanisms are
before we start to observe something
right so so a lot of what i hear from
you is that a lot of the signs that that
that we look at so a lot of clinical
science is based on
a syndromic diagnosis so we're saying
that this this
this patient group shares a certain set
of signs and symptoms
and if it's that then we give it a name
and that's a useful thing to give it a
name so we have a working hypothesis and
can talk about it
but along the line of this process of
discovering what is actually going on
we are kind of taking this diagnosis as
something set
as something that exists as an as an
entity rather than a working hypothesis
so then we start to developing drugs to
fix a problem
so to fix the signs and symptoms which
is a good idea for those who do have the
signs and symptoms
so it's at least very promising if you
do suffer of ms as the
the example you gave if there are
solutions to the problem that i
experienced to the signs and symptoms
that's a useful thing
but we could recognize that this is like
a painkiller
rather than something that really
addresses the cause of disease so what
might be the steps for us what would be
the structural approach to take in the
future so that we're actually turning
our direction and really drill down to
the cause of disease rather than trying
to fix signs and symptoms
yeah and you know don't get me wrong
symptomatic medicine and palliative care
and
you know ameliorating some of the
the um advancement of pathology like
this awesome
novocaine is one of the best inventions
ever dentistry totally sucked before
novocaine
so uh that's not addressing something at
a causal level but it's awesome right
so but we can do so much
better and
there's a place where okay so let's say
i'm looking at the relationship between
the regulatory bodies
so in the us the fda in particular other
bodies ama and whatever but let's
look at the fda for is this a treatment
that
can actually a doctor can give to treat
a disease right so the disease has been
recognized the treatment's been
recognized and
otherwise the doctor's not allowed to
use it insurance won't cover it whatever
right
so we look at what it takes to get the
regulatory
status which also means then that it
will get trained to new people in
medical school
well so phase three clinical trials are
going to cost
a billion dollars most of a billion
dollars but now factoring all the things
that don't make it through
matriculating that right a billion
dollars and
so the only way to ever be able to
recoup that money
is if i can patent the thing because
otherwise
someone else who's just competing on
cost of goods and they didn't put the
billion dollars up
it was just going to beat me and so if
i'm looking at patentable stuff then i
look at the regulatory dynamics around
patenting i can only patent synthetic
molecules
and that means that the things i'm
looking at are not part of how your body
worked when it was healthy and are not
part of the evolutionary environments
that made humans in the first place
at all ever so what's the chance we're
going to be able to do health promotion
with weird synthetic molecules that were
never part of the original picture
because
the intersection of the regulatory
landscape
and ip law and the financialization of
the research
make it to where we can't even study the
right stuff so let's say i looked at
when the same person with the same
genome didn't have cancer and they were
super healthy and now that they have
cancer what was different in their body
or before the autoimmune disease and i
see that there are certain
cell types and certain peptides that are
much more
prevalent and other ones that are less
prevalent and i'd start to think about
types of biological endogenous medicine
i could do
i i can't even research most of that
because i'll never be able to patent it
which means there's no money for the
research
to ever be able to get it through
clinical approval so
basically the epistemology that looks
for
sick one drug i mean one disease
a set of symptoms one drug it's totally
dumb epistemology
but the there is no incentive to be able
to try and do better complex
epistemology from a finance regulatory
point of view so
the epistemics are actually
straightforward which is
acute causation acute singular causation
is straightforward you got a physical
injury that was an acute injury
we're going to sew it up don't do that
thing again right
or you had an acute infectious exposure
we're going to give you the antibiotic
for it
even that starts getting questionable
because did everyone who is exposed get
the same thing and do you actually have
underlying immune weakness
and is the antibiotic actually necessary
and are you breeding antibiotic
resistance in the whole population by
using it unnecessarily
there's questions there but let's just
say there are times where that's true
an acute thing but
most disease does not have a single
cause
and the causes so they're multifactorial
they're different for different people
and many of them are radically time
delayed
and so to actually be able to do
curative work we've actually got to be
able to assess how the regulatory
systems of the body are doing
and what the deviations to homeodynamics
the person has been exposed to are find
the unique set be able to
specially reverse that unique set and
generally support the homeodynamic
systems of the body
it's a totally different way of thinking
about medicine so one of the
so we're talking about in a way you talk
about personalized medicine precision
medicine
terms that have been used in different
ways but let's say
n equals one medicine
now part of how research is done right
now
is is to understand what is going on in
a single case
by looking at similar cases and
comparing them and trying to understand
the pattern
so what we do the approach to research
is to kind of look at the
disease from the outside and recognize
patterns of disease that are similar
come
in a group of people that we observe
that is essentially different to the
disease experience of the person who had
this threshold
this multifactorial threshold experience
how do we so it's basically the way we
conduct research
today is completely missing the point
it's not useless
right like
clinical trials aren't totally useless
being able to do variable isolation and
seeing what that variable does across
the distribution of all the other
variables gives us an insight right so
when we do a clinical trial on a drug
compared to a placebo and we're trying
to see is there some effect beyond the
placebo and we see there is versus there
isn't there is indicates that there is
some
mechanism that's occurring that's kind
of all it tells us that there's some
mechanism
but the fact that there's a gaussian
distribution of the response curve where
some people have great responses and
some maybe have terrible responses
is a result of lots of other things that
are going on that we
don't recognize so they just get put
under a bell curve and it would be much
more interesting
if we could start to figure that stuff
out well you can't do that
with looking with variable isolation on
a large population
so now when i move all the way to n
equals one where i'm looking at a
population of one and trying to look at
all the variables and look at how they
make sense together i've got it
now i've got to use complexity science
i've got to use much more advanced kind
of statistical modeling
but there are ways of simplifying it
because we know that if i just try and
do the brute force computation
there are things we can't measure right
so i can
i can put a qeg on you but i can't see
subcortical structures there's no good
way to see that in real time there's
lots of proteins we can't measure
and and there's that we just don't
even know that we don't know about yet
that is
a huge part of it and if i tried to run
optimization on it it's
not computable these are np hard
problems but i can
i can collapse that entire space to ways
of thinking about it that makes sense
which is
is the system not getting enough of
something it needs is it getting too
much of something
to be able to process well like this is
kind of chinese medicine ayurvedic
medicine basics but that we can
modernize
so is it not getting enough of something
is it not getting enough
exercise rest love affection sunlight
micronutrients macronutrients so let's
say we look at micronutrients
we need to think about subclinical
deficiency as opposed to clinical
deficiency so
most people don't have scurvy right
that's awesome that they don't have
scurvy
but if we look at optimal vitamin c and
then we look at scurvy
there's a pretty big range in here that
is don't yet have scurvy but that is
sub-optimal so we'd call that
sub-clinical deficiency where
being able to augment those levels would
make a difference now
because i've got so many micronutrients
to look at if i just try to control that
one variable and look at
decreased all-cause mortality or
whatever it's going to be really hard to
tell
because that one thing also needs
bioflavonoid synergistically to work and
it's going to interact
like there's so many other things going
on so if i start to look
overarchingly at are we providing
good nutrition and is this person
absorbing and assimilating it
and dealing with subclinical deficiency
also toxicity so
until we have re-engineered our supply
chains
do i want to look at the exposure people
have to heavy metals to vocs to
mycotoxins
also to infections that are subclinical
meaning they're not creating acute
medical symptomology but this is not a
normal part of a human microbiome
and when we look at nh pylori or an hpv
or an ebv that we know have statistical
correlations with diseases that are
chronic infections there's a gazillion
other things that do
functional medicine and kind of
functional infectious explorative
medicine are starting to pioneer this
more than general medicine
but this is too much of something that
the body shouldn't have
we can do stuff about that so there's a
way of taking this entire search base
and optimization space and having some
kind of heuristic diagnostics that are
able to get
do a lot of the work more simply we can
also think about the primary regulatory
mechanisms of the body and how to look
at the robustness of them
which indicates everything that's going
on so like
i want to be able to look not just at
the
homeostatic state is your vitamin d your
heart rate your cholesterol within a
level
i want to look at the homeodynamic
capacity that when i stress it how far
out does it go and how quickly does it
come back
because if we don't just want to define
disease we want to define health in a
way we can measure
if we want to start to think about the
objectivity of it then i would define
health as
related to the robustness of the
homeodynamic
regulatory mechanisms how much stress
the being can be exposed to without
going into pathophysiology without
deviating from the homeodynamics
so we that's a different set of tests we
need to stress test stuff
right and so i would like to see more of
those things
then we can define disease as
some of those homeodynamic markers are
actually out of range
and pathophysiology is occurring aging
is not yet disease they're in range but
there's less robustness which means
more susceptibility to disease meaning
smaller stresses can cause larger strain
and so then the kind of anti-aging um
preventative
preventative health promotion work is
just increasing the robustness of the
regulatory mechanism so we both want to
measure and think about the body's
regulatory dynamics and how to promote
those generally
as well as look at the specific causes
of
pathology and how to reverse them
specifically
beautiful thank you so when we you're
talking about
homeodynamic systems so basically the
regulations
all the different regulatory processes
going on within the body
that maintain some sort of range of what
we perceive
within the realm of ease rather than
this ease which is probably then at the
outliers of the bells curve
so when we look at
when we look at these regulatory
mechanisms
within a system we still assume that
body
is a closed system
and i wonder from what you said before
whether that's actually an assumption we
should take
or whether we should also look at a
perspective that
assumes that this body has
probably some mechanisms that run within
but probably also it is at least
susceptible to or interfering with
mechanisms that
that are around that body so in this
okay so let's look at layers of
holisticness and
or comprehensivity and consideration so
we can't just do the vertical slices
called neurology gastroenterology
rheumatology oncology because most of
the
complex things occur across those right
if we look at brain access dynamics
that's gastroenterology neurology
immunology rheumatology all mixed
together where no specialist is going to
see the thing
right so we have to look at the
interaction of all the body systems
we also have to look at the horizontal
slices the omics of
it's not just what's happening at the
genomic level in the epigenetic and the
proteomic but also how the top-down
connectomic stuff
and neuroendocrine stuff is affecting
the bottom up stuff so we want to think
about all the body systems together
but then it's not just the body systems
of the individual it's the body and
mind psyche emotion spirit of the
individual right so we want to be
thinking about how all of those interact
but then it's not just the individuals
the individual interacting
with the greater world and universe
they're part of both
physically and psychologically right
metaphysically
so physically i find the person has
mycotoxins and i send them home to a
house that still has mold in it
like obviously we have to address the
physical environment they're in
or we know very clearly that
the lifestyle of people is going to be
affected by the lifestyle of the people
they're spending a lot of time around
more than almost anything else
so the person has illnesses associated
with obesity and i send them home
to an environment and a community in
which the health habits of everyone suck
and are self-reinforcing
and would be ostracizing if they did
something different
or were the persons really lonely and
loneliness we know drives addiction
so i i've got to think about the
s the physiological and psychological
interactions of the being with their
environment and what's necessary so
when we think about a integrative or a
holistic
medicine or healthcare it has to factor
all that so to what degree
is a sense of isolation or separation
a cause of disease whether it's the
subjective experience
of feeling separated is that is that a
statement you could go along with that
that
the sense of separation is is a sense
that i might create but it is an
illusionary sense
whilst there is nothing but a connect
an interconnectedness so as soon as i
perceive myself
as separate from that one
interconnectedness
this is a cause of disease
when you say that the disconnection is
illusory well that
is true on some levels
it's also switching the burden to the
individual
perception where maybe they actually
have
social dynamics that really are
ostracizing or really are don't have
real connection and
of course insofar as i'm talking to the
individual i want to help them figure
out how
they can take more agency to change
their life but in so far as i'm thinking
about how to change systems i want to
say how do we make systems that support
individuals more
that's kind of the classically right and
left perspective individual or
collective focus you have to do both and
pay attention to the virtuous cycle
between them
when you look at work of people like
gabor mate and others on attachment
theory and how much
the sense of isolation drives
addiction which then drives so many
other things
from a health perspective i think this
is huge
but it's also like
when we look at mass shooters
none of them that i'm aware of had
healthy meaningful relationships before
being mass shooters
so news goes and interviews and says
they were
all the neighbors the neighbors say the
person was alone or they totally kept
themselves nobody ever saw them
which means that person was getting per
to progress
in their how disenfranchised they felt
how depressed how misanthropic they were
with nobody knowing and checking which
is also why i don't want a world that
allows
people that makes it very easy for
people to
be isolated that much so if amazon's
going to come deliver the stuff at the
door and my doctor on the phone can do
that
people can be progressing in their
psychopathology radically and then
having access to
more destructive tools than earlier
humans had
right now ar-15s and beyond that
weaponized drones
right so it's not just that the
isolation is bad for the person it's
that the isolation makes those people
very dangerous to
the health of the society as a whole
and so it's actually important that as
we're thinking about redesigning
civilization we're making the processes
by which people
get their basic resources provisioned
and needs met involve interacting with
other
humans in healthy enriching ways
otherwise
the intersection of people that are
progressing in psychopathology with
decentralized catastrophic technology
is a major problem for the world yeah
thank you thank you for all your
insights that you have shared with us
it's become very clear to me that when
we
change when we direct our attention
towards health and less on
disease there's no way we can limit it
to
an individual we have to think
systemically
there's no way we get we can limit it to
the consultation room
we have to think about the environment
the immediate environment the social
environment
and and all the other major parameters
um that we that constitute health
uh in terms of social environments in
terms of agriculture in terms of
environmental pollution
and we didn't we only touched on the
financial aspects and how
the um how markets
driving um the healthcare system
as it is at the moment having a major
impact
thank you very much for giving us such
an extraordinary broad overview
thank you daniel thank you what a great
pleasure to have you here
daniel spencer
this has been heart based medicine
production thanks for listening